Unlock the secret to the greatest mystery the world has ever known.
Atlantis: The Lost Empire is a animation, family,
adventure film directed by Gary Trousdale.
A young linguist named Milo Thatch joins an intrepid group of
explorers to find the mysterious lost continent of Atlantis.
Milo James Thatch (voice), played by Michael J. Fox.
Princess 'Kida' Kidagakash (voice), played by Cree Summer.
Commander Lyle Tiberius Rourke (voice), played by James Garner.
Helga Katrina Sinclair (voice), played by Claudia Christian.
Gaetan 'The Mole' Moliere (voice), played by Corey Burton.
Dr. Joshua Strongbear Sweet (voice), played by Phil Morris.
Atlantis: The Lost Empire is a 2001 American animated action adventure film directed by Gary
Trousdale and Kirk Wise, produced by Don Hahn, and written by Tab Murphy.
Produced by Walt Disney Feature Animation, it stars Michael J.
Fox, James Garner, Cree Summer, Don Novello, Phil Morris, Claudia Christian, Jacqueline Obradors,
Florence Stanley, David Ogden Stiers, John Mahoney, Jim Varney, Corey Burton and Leonard Nimoy.
Set in 1914, it follows young linguist Milo Thatch, who gains possession of a sacred book, which
he believes will guide him and a crew of mercenaries to the lost city of Atlantis.
Development of the film began after production had
finished on The Hunchback of Notre Dame (1996).
Instead of another musical, directors Trousdale and Wise, producer Hahn, and screenwriter
Murphy decided to do an adventure film inspired by the works of Jules Verne.
Atlantis: The Lost Empire was notable for adopting the distinctive visual style of
comic book artist Mike Mignola, one of the film's production designers.
The film made greater use of computer-generated imagery (CGI) than any of Disney's previous
traditionally animated features and remains one of the few to have been shot in anamorphic format.
Linguist Marc Okrand constructed an Atlantean
language specifically for use in the film.
James Newton Howard provided the film's musical score.
The film was released at a time when audience interest in animated films was
shifting away from traditional animation toward films with full CGI.
Atlantis: The Lost Empire premiered at the El Capitan Theatre in Hollywood, Los
Angeles, on June 3, 2001, and went into its general release on June 15.
The film received mixed reviews from critics.
Budgeted at around $90–120 million, Atlantis grossed over $186 million worldwide, $84 million of which was earned in North America; its lackluster box office
response was identified as a result of being released in competition with Shrek, Lara Croft: Tomb Raider, The Fast and the Furious and Dr.
Dolittle 2.
As a result of the film's box office failure, Disney cancelled a planned spin-off animated television series, Team
Atlantis; an underwater Disneyland attraction; and a volcanic Magic Kingdom attraction based on it.
Atlantis was nominated for several awards, including seven Annie Awards,
and won Best Sound Editing at the 2002 Golden Reel Awards.
The film was released on VHS and DVD on January 29,
2002, and on Blu-ray on June 11, 2013.
Despite its initial reception, reception in later years became favorable and has given Atlantis a cult following and
reappraisal from critics as a mistreated classic, due in part to Mignola's unique artistic influence.
A direct-to-video sequel, Atlantis: Milo's Return, was released in 2003.
The film explores themes of sea, submarine, mediterranean, atlantis, expedition.
The tone is thought_provoking.